const quizzes = [{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"What are two responsibilities that you will have as a British citizen or permanent resident of the UK?","choices":["To look after the area in which you live and the environment","To look after yourself and your family","To stay in the UK forever","To promote work in your local community"],"correct":[0,1],"explanation":"If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should: look after yourself and your family, look after the area in which you live and the environment, respect and obey the law, respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions and treat others with fairness."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where is Big Ben located?","choices":["Buckingham Palace","The Tower of London","Trafalgar Square","The Houses of the Parliament"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Big Ben is the nickname for the great bell of the clock at the Houses of Parliament in London."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"When were men and women given the right to vote at the age of 21?","choices":["1918","1903","1928","1923"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In 1928, women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Where is the UK geographically located?","choices":["South west of Europe","North east of Europe","North west of Europe","South east of Europe"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The UK is located in the north west of Europe."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who is the patron Saint of Scotland?","choices":["St David","St Patrick","St George","St Andrew"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The patron Saint of Scotland is St Andrew."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which two houses fought in the Wars of the Roses?","choices":["The House of Chester","The House of York","The House of Lancaster","The House of Newcastle"],"correct":[1,2],"explanation":"The Wars of the Roses were fought between the supporters of two families: the House of Lancaster and the House of York."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"The Bill of Rights of 1689 confirmed the right to vote for all adult men.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Bill of Rights, 1689, confirmed the rights of Parliament and the limits of the king's power."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the Cenotaph?","choices":["A flower","A Christian church","A war memorial","A theatre"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Cenotaph is a war memorial and it is the site of the annual Remembrance Day service attended by the King, politicians and foreign ambassadors."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was the first female Prime Minister of the UK?","choices":["Mary Stuart","Theresa May","Margaret Thatcher","Florence Nightingale"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Margaret Thatcher was the first woman Prime Minister of the UK."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Who chairs the debates at the House of Commons?","choices":["A bishop","The Prime Minister","The Speaker","The archbishop of Canterbury"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Debates in the House of Commons are chaired by the Speaker."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was the captain of the English football team that won the World Cup in 1966?","choices":["Sir Roger Bannister","Sir Jackie Stewart","Sir Ian Botham","Bobby Moore"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Bobby Moore captained the English football team that won the World Cup in 1966."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When did the English defeat the Spanish Armada?","choices":["1466","1066","1254","1588"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 1588 the English defeated the Spanish Armada."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Anyone can make a complaint about the police by writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What is the minimum age required to serve on a jury?","choices":["16","18","21","25"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18 to 70 can be asked to serve on a jury."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How is a jury selected?","choices":["From the NHS registration system","Randomly from the electoral register","Alphabetically from the telephone directory","From a postcode selection"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"As well as getting the right to vote, people on the electoral register are randomly selected to serve on a jury. Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18 to 70 can be asked to do this."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is a bank holiday?","choices":["A public holiday when banks are open all day","A public holiday for people working in banks","An additional day off that every worker in the UK is entitled to","A public holiday when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"There are public holidays each year called bank holidays, when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What will you be given to vote before a general election takes place?","choices":["A ballot slip","A poll card","A voting slip","A poll tax relief"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Before the election you will be sent a poll card."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Solicitors' charges are usually based on how much time they spend on a case","Solicitors' charges are usually based on the nature of a case and its importance"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Solicitors' charges are usually based on how much time they spend on a case."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"By law, which TWO types of media have to give a balanced coverage of all political parties and equal time to rival viewpoints before an election?","choices":["Television","Internet","Newspapers","Radio"],"correct":[0,3],"explanation":"By law, radio and television coverage of the political parties must be balanced and so equal time has to be given to rival viewpoints."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following territories is a Crown dependency but is NOT part of the UK?","choices":["Northern Ireland","Wales","The Channel Islands","Scotland"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Channel Islands is a British overseas territory linked to the UK, but it is not part of it."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What did Sir Frank Whittle invent in the 1930s?","choices":["Radar","Hovercraft","Jet engine","Ballpoint pen"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The jet engine was developed in Britain in the 1930s by Sir Frank Whittle."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who wrote 'The Daffodils'?","choices":["William Blake","Robert Browning","Lord Byron","William Wordsworth"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The British poet William Wordsworth wrote 'The Daffodils'."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was given the title of Lord Protector?","choices":["Charles I","Charles II","Winston Churchill","Oliver Cromwell"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Oliver Cromwell was given the title of Lord Protector and ruled until his death in 1658."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What are the 40 days before Easter called?","choices":["Diwali","Lent","Hannukah","Vaisakhi"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The 40 days before Easter are known as Lent."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What is the Home Secretary responsible for?","choices":["Health","Defence","Education","Policing"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Home Secretary is responsible for crime, policing, and immigration."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"St Helena is a British overseas territory and it is part of the United Kingdom.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"British overseas territories, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands, are linked to the UK but are not part of it."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Several Church of England bishops sit in the House of Lords.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"When walking your dog in a public place, you must ensure:","choices":["That your dog does not play with other dogs","That your dog wears a collar showing the name and address of the owner","That your dog wears a high visibility jacket","That your dog does not bark"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"All dogs in public places must wear a collar showing the name and address of the owner."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Women over the age of 30 were given the right to vote as a result of their contribution towards the war effort. Which war was that?","choices":["The Second World War","The Crimean War","The First World War","The Civil War"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights and the right to stand for Parliament, partly in recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"When did Ireland become a republic?","choices":["1925","1939","1949","1927"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Ireland became a republic in 1949."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where did the first farmers come from?","choices":["South-west Europe","South-east Europe","North-east America","North-west Asia"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The first farmers arrived in Britain 6,000 years ago. The ancestors of these first farmers probably came from south-east Europe."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Who was an important contributor to the 'pop art' movement of the 1960's?","choices":["David Hockney","Lucian Freud","John Petts","Henry Moore"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"David Hockney was an important contributor to the 'pop art' movement of the 1960s and continues to be influential today."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who became Prime Minister and was an inspirational leader to the British people during WWII?","choices":["Winston Churchill","Clement Attlee","Margaret Thatcher","Sir Robert Walpole"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Winston Churchill."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who led the first invasion of Britain?","choices":["Emperor Hadrian","Julius Caesar","Canute","William, the Duke of Normandy"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Julius Caesar led a Roman invasion of Britain in 55 BC. This was unsuccessful and for nearly 100 years Britain remained separate from the Roman Empire. In AD 43 the Emperor Claudius led the Roman army in a new invasion. This time, there was resistance from some of the British tribes but the Romans were successful in occupying almost all of Britain."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Under which king did the Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England unite to defeat the Vikings?","choices":["William of Orange","King Alfred the Great","Henry VIII","Robert the Bruce"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England united under King Alfred the Great, who defeated the Vikings."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When was the Magna Carta created?","choices":["1514","1215","1415","1314"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Magna Carta was created in 1215."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Northern Ireland has its own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following plays was written by William Shakespeare?","choices":["Pride and Prejudice","A Midsummer Night's dream","Sense and Sensibility","Great Expectations"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"William Shakespeare's most famous plays include A Midsummer Night's dream."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How many members does a jury have in England, Wales and Northern Ireland?","choices":["9","12","15","20"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In England, Wales, and Northern Ireland a jury has 12 members."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Which two of the following religious communities celebrate Diwali?","choices":["Buddhists","Hindus","Jews","Sikhs"],"correct":[1,3],"explanation":"Diwali is celebrated by Hindus and Sikhs."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What is Good Friday?","choices":["The day when Jesus Christ rose from the dead","The day when Jesus Christ was born","The day when Jesus Christ died","The day when Jesus Christ became 30 years old"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Good Friday marks the death of Jesus Christ during Easter."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"St Patrick's day is a public holiday in Northern Ireland.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Only Scotland and Northern Ireland have their patron saint's day as an official holiday (although in Scotland not all businesses and offices will close)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which was the last successful foreign invasion of England that took place in 1066?","choices":["The Viking invasion","The Anglo-Saxon Conquest","The Roman invasion","The Norman Conquest"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Norman Conquest was the last successful foreign invasion of England in 1066."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which sport can be traced back to the 15th century in Scotland?","choices":["Golf","Tennis","Football","Rugby"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The modern game of golf can be traced back to 15th-century Scotland."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the first person in England to print books using a printing press?","choices":["William Shakespeare","John Barbour","Geoffrey Chaucer","William Caxton"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"William Caxton was the first person in England to print books using a printing press."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which court deals with minor criminal cases in England, Wales and Northern Ireland?","choices":["High Court","Justice of the Peace Court","Magistrates' Court","Crown Court"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In England, Wales, and Northern Ireland, most minor criminal cases are dealt with in a Magistrates' Court. In Scotland, minor criminal offences go to a Justice of the Peace Court."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What did the Scottish John Logie Baird develop?","choices":["Television","Radar","Personal computer","Radio"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The television was developed by Scotsman John Logie Baird in the 1920s."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where are the Crown Jewels kept?","choices":["At the House of Commons","At the Tower of London","At Buckingham Palace","At Windsor Castle"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Crown Jewels are kept at the Tower of London."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following is a fundamental principle of British life?","choices":["Communism","Intolerance","Individual liberty","Inequity"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Individual liberty is a fundamental principle of British life."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Wales has its own established church.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"There is no established Church in Wales or Northern Ireland."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"How is New Year's Eve called in Scotland?","choices":["Vaisakhi","Hannukah","Diwali","Hogmanay"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In Scotland, the 31st of December (New Year's Eve) is called Hogmanay."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Why did Henry VIII establish the church of England?","choices":["Because the Pope didn't let him divorce his first wife, Catherine of Aragon","Because the Pope didn't let him marry Catherine Howard","Because the Pope wanted England to be a Catholic country","Because the Pope didn't let him divorce his wife, Anne of Cleves"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"To divorce his first wife, Henry needed the approval of the Pope. When the Pope refused, Henry established the church of England."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the long war that English kings fought with France in the middle ages?","choices":["The Crimean War","The First World War","The Hundred Years War","The Boer War"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"English kings fought a long war with France, called the Hundred Years War (even though it actually lasted 116 years)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was supported by clansmen from the Scottish highlands and raised and army in 1745?","choices":["Bonnie Prince Charlie","Robert Burns","Oliver Cromwell","Kenneth MacAlpin"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"In 1745 there was another attempt to put a Stuart king back on the throne in place of George I's son, George II. Charles Edward Stuart (Bonnie Prince Charlie), the grandson of James II, landed in Scotland. He was supported by clansmen from the Scottish highlands and raised an army."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"If you think someone is trying to persuade you to join an extremist or terrorist activity, who should you contact?","choices":["The Home Office","Your local police force","Your local MP","Your family"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"If you think someone is trying to persuade you to join an extremist or terrorist cause, you should notify your local police force."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"It is compulsory for 16 and 17-year-olds to join the National Citizen Service programme.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The National Citizen Service programme, which gives 16- and 17-year-olds the opportunity to enjoy outdoor activities, develop their skills and take part in a community project. Therefore, it is optional."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What is the name of the tour guides that tell visitors stories about the Tower of London's history?","choices":["Knights","Chartists","Suffragettes","Beefeaters"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Tours are given at the Tower of London by the Yeoman Warders, also known as Beefeaters, who tell visitors about the building's history."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which two countries developed the Concorde, the world's only supersonic commercial airliner?","choices":["Italy","Britain","Germany","France"],"correct":[1,3],"explanation":"Britain and France developed the world's only supersonic commercial airliner, Concorde."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where is Snowdonia located?","choices":["Scotland","Wales","England","Northern Ireland"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Snowdonia is in Wales."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who wrote Sherlock Holmes?","choices":["Evelyn Waugh","Sir Kingsley Amis","Graham Greene","Sir Arthur Conan Doyle"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Sir Arthur Conan Doyle is the author of Sherlock Holmes."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which country was invaded by Germany in 1939?","choices":["Austria","Italy","Russia","Poland"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Germany invaded Poland in 1939."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Who is the patron Saint of Wales?","choices":["St David","St George","St Patrick","St Andrew"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The patron Saint of Wales is St David."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Lake District is the largest national park of England.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the area in London where famous theatres are located?","choices":["Soho","Theatreland","Westminster","Hyde Park"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"London's west end, also known as 'Theatreland', is particularly well known for its theatres."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which two of the following are key roles of school governors?","choices":["Monitoring student's behaviour","Monitoring and evaluating school performance","Setting the strategic direction of the school","Giving awards to the best students of the school"],"correct":[1,2],"explanation":"Governors and school boards have an important part to play in raising school standards. They have three key roles: setting the strategic direction of the school, ensuring accountability and monitoring and evaluating school performance."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What led the American colonies to want their independence from Britain?","choices":["The British government wanted to control their borders","They were running out of resources","The British government wanted to tax them","There were not enough jobs for the local people"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The British government wanted to tax the colonies."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was the leader of the suffragettes, the group that campaigned for women's rights to vote?","choices":["Queen Victoria","Oliver Cromwell","Florence Nightingale","Emmeline Pankhurst"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Emmeline Pankhurst was the leader of the suffragettes."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Cardiff is the capital city of which country?","choices":["Scotland","Northern Ireland","Ireland","Wales"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The capital city of Wales is Cardiff."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"During the Great Depression in the 1930s which industry was badly affected?","choices":["Housing construction","Shipbuilding","Automobile","Aviation"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"During the 'Great Depression' in the 1930s the traditional heavy industries such as shipbuilding were badly affected."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the first man in the world to run 1 mile in under 4 minutes?","choices":["Sir Chris Hoy","Sir Roger Bannister","David Weir","Mo Farah"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Sir Roger Bannister was the first man in the world to run a mile in under four minutes, in 1954."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Which festival celebrates the end of Ramadan, when Muslims have fasted for a month?","choices":["Hannukah","Vaisakhi","Eid ul Adha","Eid al-Fitr"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Eid al-Fitr celebrates the end of Ramadan, when Muslims have fasted for a month."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When did the 'Black Death' take place?","choices":["The Golden Age","The Stone Age","The Middle Ages","The Iron Age"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In 1348 (Middle Ages) the 'Black\n"},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was the last battle between Great Britain and France?","choices":["The Battle of Trafalgar","The Battle of Waterloo","The Battle of Hastings","Battle of Agincourt"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In 1815, the French Wars ended with the defeat of the Emperor Napoleon by the Duke of Wellington at the Battle of Waterloo."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which flower is associated with Wales?","choices":["Daffodil","Rose","Shamrock","Thistle"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The flower associated with Wales is the daffodil."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"During the reign of Charles II parts of London were destroyed, what was the cause of this destruction?","choices":["A war","A flood","A fire","An earthquake"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"During Charles II's reign, a great fire destroyed much of the city, including many churches and St Paul's Cathedral."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How often are general elections held in the UK?","choices":["Every 3 years","Every 4 years","Every 5 years","Every 10 years"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"MPs are elected at a General Election, which is held at least every five years."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Scotland has its own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What charity works to preserve important buildings, coastline and countryside in the UK?","choices":["Shelter","Age UK","Crisis","The National Trust"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The National Trust is a charity that works to preserve important buildings, coastline and countryside in the UK."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Great Britain refers only to England, Wales and Scotland.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the tribal leader who fought against the Romans?","choices":["Cleopatra","Claudia","Boudicca","St Augustine"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans was Boudicca, the queen of the Iceni in what is now eastern England."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was voted the greatest Briton of all time in 2002?","choices":["Isaac Newton","Winston Churchill","Alexander Fleming","Mo Farat"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Winston Churchill remains a much-admired figure to this day, and in 2002 was voted the greatest Briton of all time by the public."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which two houses form the UK Parliament?","choices":["The House of Lords","House of Members","House of Commons","House of Fraser"],"correct":[0,2],"explanation":"The UK Parliament is formed of the House of Commons and the House of Lords."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"When did women get the right to vote at the same age as men?","choices":["1918","1928","1938","1948"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In 1928, women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Who is the head of the Church of England?","choices":["The Prime Minister","The Archbishop of Canterbury","The Pope","The monarch"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The monarch is the head of the Church of England."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What sort of event is the Grand National?","choices":["Rugby","Golf","Horse Racing","Tennis"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Grand National is a horse racing event."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What type of literature are the Canterbury Tales?","choices":["Poems","Novels","Jokes","Fables"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series of poems in English about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"When is Christmas Day?","choices":["24th of December","25th of December","26th of December","27th of December"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Christmas Day is celebrated on the 25th of December."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who supported King Charles I during the Civil War?","choices":["Roundheads","Suffragettes","Quakers","Cavaliers"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"During the civil war between the king and Parliament the country split into those who supported the king (the Cavaliers) and those who supported Parliament (the Roundheads)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What battle is commemorated in the Bayeux Tapestry?","choices":["The Battle of Waterloo","The Battle of Trafalgar","The Battle of Hastings","The Battle of Britain"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Battle of Hastings is commemorated in a great piece of embroidery, known as the Bayeux tapestry."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where was Anne Boleyn, the wife of Henry VIII, executed?","choices":["Houses of the Parliament","Stonehenge","Tower of London","Whitehall"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Anne Boleyn was unpopular in the country and was accused of taking lovers. She was executed at the Tower of London."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Racial crime and smoking in public places are examples of:","choices":["Civil offences","Criminal offences"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Racial crime and smoking in public places are examples of criminal offences."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What type of character was played by Charlie Chaplin?","choices":["A superhero","A tramp","A scientific genius","A bandit"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Sir Charles (Charlie) Chaplin became famous in silent movies for his tramp character and was one of many British actors to make a career in Hollywood."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"You have to be at least 21 years old to stand as MP.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"This statement is false. Anyone aged 18 or over can stand for election as an MP but they are unlikely to win unless they have been nominated to represent one of the major political parties."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who developed the radar?","choices":["John Logie Baird","Sir Frank Whittle","Sir Christopher Cockrell","Sir Robert Watson-Watt"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Sir Robert Watson-Watt developed the radar."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Where is the official home of the Prime Minister?","choices":["18 Oxford Street","Buckingham Palace","Windsor Castle","10 Downing Street"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The official home of the Prime Minister is 10 Downing Street."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"By law, which TWO types of media have to give a balanced coverage of all political parties and equal time to rival viewpoints before an election?","choices":["Television","Internet","Newspapers","Radio"],"correct":[0,3],"explanation":"By law, radio and television coverage of the political parties must be balanced and so equal time has to be given to rival viewpoints."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"When does Easter take place?","choices":["November or December","January or February","March or April","May or June"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Easter takes place in March or April."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which of the following is not a valid UK coin?","choices":["1p","5p","25p","£1"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"There are no 25p coins in the UK currency."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where is the Eden Project located?","choices":["Dorset","Cornwall","Devon","Somerset"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Eden Project is located in Cornwall, in the south west of England."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"St Helena and the Falkland Islands are part of Great Britain.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"There are several British overseas territories in other parts of the world, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands. They are also linked to the UK but are not part of it."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which two of the following are fundamental principles of British life?","choices":["Monarchy","The rule of law","Democracy","Join a political party"],"correct":[1,2],"explanation":"The fundamental principles of British life include: democracy, the rule of law, individual liberty, tolerance of those with different faiths and beliefs and participation in community life."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Where should you register if you want to become part of a jury?","choices":["The electoral register","Your local church","The NHS","The British Embassy"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"People on the electoral register are randomly selected to serve on a jury. Therefore, if you want to be selected to form part of a jury you have to be on the electoral register and be between 18 to 70 years old."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What sort of church is the Church of Scotland?","choices":["Catholic","Baptist","Presbyterian","Methodist"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In Scotland, the national Church is the Church of Scotland, which is a Presbyterian Church."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Where does golf come from?","choices":["Wales","Australia","Ireland","Scotland"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The modern game of golf can be traced back to 15th century Scotland."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"When do the television and newspapers have stories that are jokes until midday?","choices":["Valentine's Day","Boxing Day","Halloween","April Fool's Day"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"On April Fool's Day, the 1st of April the television and newspapers often have stories that are April Fool jokes."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What king was defeated by Oliver Cromwell during the Civil War and hid in an oak tree before escaping to Europe?","choices":["Richard III","Charles II","James I","Henry IV"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The correct answer is Charles II."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the father of Queen Elizabeth I?","choices":["Edward I","Henry V","Henry VII","Henry VIII"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The father of Queen Elizabeth I was Henry VIII."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Complaints against the police can ONLY be made by writing to the Police Complaints Commissioner.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Anyone can make a complaint about the police by going to a police station and writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved. Complaints can also be made to an independent body: the Independent Police Complaints Commission in England and Wales, the Police Complaints Commissioner for Scotland or the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Who is the patron Saint of Northern Ireland?","choices":["St George","St Patrick","St Andrew","St David"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The patron Saint of Northern Ireland is St Patrick."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the period when new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed?","choices":["The Enlightenment","The Glorious Revolution","The Swinging Sixties","The Reformation"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"During the 18th century, new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed. This is often called 'the Enlightenment'."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following statements is true:","choices":["Mary Stuart ('Mary, Queen of Scots') was a Protestant","Mary Stuart ('Mary, Queen of Scots') was a Catholic"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Mary Stuart ('Mary, Queen of Scots') was a Catholic."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following is an example of civil law?","choices":["To sell tobacco products to anyone under the age of 18","To buy alcohol for people who are under the age of 18","Discrimination in the workplace","To carry a weapon of any kind, even if it is for self-defence"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Discrimination in the workplace is an example of civil law."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"In which battle did Admiral Nelson die?","choices":["The Battle of Hastings","The Battle of Waterloo","The Battle of Trafalgar","The Battle of Bannockburn"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar and was killed in the battle."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"William of Orange was asked by Protestants to invade England and proclaim himself king. But, when William reached England, there was no resistance and he took over the throne. This event was later known as:","choices":["The 'Glorious Revolution'","The Restoration","The 'Great Depression'","The 'Blitz'"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"William of Orange was asked by Protestants to invade England and proclaim himself king. When William reached England, there was no resistance and he took over the throne. This event was later called the 'Glorious Revolution'."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What sort of charity is 'Friends of the Earth'?","choices":["An environmental charity","A medical research charity","A charity working with pets","A charity working with older people"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Friends of the Earth is an environmental charity."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"If a husband forces his wife to have sex he can be charged with rape.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"In which country of the British Empire did the Boer War (1899-1902) take place?","choices":["Netherlands","Falkland Islands","Gibraltar","South Africa"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Boer War of 1899 to 1902 took place in South Africa with settlers from the Netherlands called the Boers."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which of the following actions is known as 'canvassing'?","choices":["Donating blood to help people","Volunteering for an environmental charity","Caring for animals at a local rescue shelter","Persuading people to vote for a political party"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Members of political parties persuade people to vote for their candidates , for instance, by handing out leaflets in the street or by knocking on people's doors and asking for their support. This is called 'canvassing'."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which novel written by JRR Tolkien was voted the country's best-loved novel in 2003?","choices":["Oliver Twist","James Bond","Pride and Prejudice","The Lord of the Rings"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 2003, the Lord of the Rings by JRR Tolkien was voted the country's best-loved novel."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When did Germany invade Poland?","choices":["1942","1941","1940","1939"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Germany invaded Poland in 1939."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"As a British citizen what are your responsibilities (choose two answers)?","choices":["To respect and obey the law","To walk your dog only during the day","To go to church on Sunday","To look after yourself and your family"],"correct":[0,3],"explanation":"If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should: respect and obey the law, look after yourself and your family, respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions, treat others with fairness and look after the area in which you live and the environment."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who made the first coins to be minted in Britain?","choices":["The people of the Stone Age","The Anglo-saxons","The people of the Iron Age","The Romans"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The people of the Iron Age made the first coins to be minted in Britain, some inscribed with the names of Iron Age kings. This marks the beginnings of British history."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who built the Tower of London?","choices":["William the Conqueror","Queen Victoria","Queen Elizabeth I","Oliver Cromwell"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The correct answer is William the Conqueror."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"There are 15 national parks in England, Wales and Scotland. What are national parks?","choices":["Giant greenhouses","Land formations of columns made from volcanic lava","Areas of protected countryside","Medieval buildings"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"National Parks are areas of protected countryside that everyone can visit, and where people live, work and look after the landscape."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Northern Ireland has its own established church.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"false. There is no established Church in Wales or Northern Ireland."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which three territories form Great Britain?","choices":["Wales","Northern Ireland","England","Scotland"],"correct":[0,2,3],"explanation":"Great Britain' refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How often are 'Prime Minister's Questions' held in the parliament?","choices":["Every day","Every week","Every two weeks","Once a month"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Prime Minister's Questions takes place every week while Parliament is sitting."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which king was executed in 1649?","choices":["James I","Charles II","James VII","Charles I"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The correct answer is Charles I."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Where was William Shakespeare born?","choices":["Manchester","Oldham","Stratford-upon-Avon","Lincolnshire"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Shakespeare was born in Stratford-upon-Avon, England."},{"type":"Sports and recreation","question":"Which two of the following are famous British Paralympians?","choices":["Dame Kelly Holmes","Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson","Jayne Torvill","Ellie Simmonds"],"correct":[1,3],"explanation":"Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson and Ellie Simmonds are the correct answers."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was reigning in England when English settlers first began to colonise the eastern coast of America?","choices":["Queen Victoria","Henry VIII","Elizabeth I","Charles II"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In Elizabeth I's time, English settlers first began to colonise the eastern coast of America."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Scotland and Wales use a system called 'individual registration' where all those entitled to vote must complete their own registration form.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"false. Northern Ireland uses a system called 'individual registration' and all those entitled to vote must complete their own registration form."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"On what day is the birth of Jesus Christ celebrated?","choices":["Father's Day","Christmas Day","New Year","Boxing Day"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Christmas Day, 25th of December, celebrates the birth of Jesus Christ."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"What sort of battle was the 'Battle of Britain', fought between Germany and Britain in the summer of 1940?","choices":["A battle in the sea","An aerial battle","A battle in the mountains","A battle without rifles"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Battle of Britain' was a crucial aerial battle fought between Germany and Britain in the summer of 1940."},{"type":"Geography and landmarks","question":"Where is Swansea located?","choices":["England","Northern Ireland","Scotland","Wales"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Swansea is located in Wales."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which two political parties formed a coalition in 2010?","choices":["The Conservative Party","The Green Party","The Labour Party","The Liberal Democrats Party"],"correct":[0,3],"explanation":"In May 2010 the Conservative and Liberal Democrat parties formed a coalition and the leader of the Conservative Party, David Cameron, became Prime Minister."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who established the Church of England?","choices":["Henry VIII","Oliver Cromwell","Winston Churchill","William of Orange"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The correct answer is Henry VIII."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"In 1348, one third of the population in England, Wales and Scotland died as a result of which disease?","choices":["Measles","Leprosy","Smallpox","The Black Death"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 1348, a disease, probably a form of plague, came to Britain. This was known as the Black Death. One third of the population of England died and a similar proportion in Scotland and Wales."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Haggis is a traditional food from which area?","choices":["Wales","England","Northern Ireland","Scotland"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Haggis is a traditional food from Scotland."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Which court deals with minor criminal offences in Scotland?","choices":["The Sheriff Court","The Magistrates' Court","The Crown Court","The Justice of the Peace Court"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In Scotland, minor criminal offences go to a Justice of the Peace Court."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which two of the following records give us information about England during the reign of William I?","choices":["The Magna Carta","The Domesday Book","The Bayeux Tapestry","The Canterbury Tales"],"correct":[1,2],"explanation":"William I aka William the conqueror.  The Domesday Book and the Bayeux Tapestry."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"In 1913, the British government promised 'Home Rule' for Ireland, why were changes in Ireland delayed until 1921?","choices":["Due to the outbreak of the First World War","Due to the outbreak of the Second World War","Because there was not a king on the British throne","Due to the outbreak of the Black Death"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The outbreak of the First World War led the British government to postpone any changes in Ireland."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following statements is true:","choices":["Elizabeth I was a Protestant and she succeeded in finding a balance between the views of the Catholics and the more extreme Protestants.","Elizabeth I was a Catholic and she succeeded in finding a balance between the views of the Catholics and the more extreme Protestants."],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Elizabeth I was a Protestant and she succeeded in finding a balance between the views of the Catholics and the more extreme Protestants."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which two documents do you need to apply for a National Insurance number?","choices":["A document with your address on it, such as a tenancy agreement","Documents that prove that you have permission to work in the UK","A contract from your employer","Documents that prove your identity"],"correct":[1,3],"explanation":"To apply for a National Insurance number you need documents that prove your identity and that you have permission to work in the UK."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"As a British citizen, you should:","choices":["Respect and obey the law","Vote in all elections","Take part in religious activities","Look after the area in which you live and the environment"],"correct":[0,3],"explanation":"As a British citizen you should respect and obey the law and look after the area in which you live and the environment are the correct answers."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"When is Halloween celebrated?","choices":["5th of November","11th of November","31st of October","1st of April"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Halloween is celebrated on the 31st of October."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"The Bill of Rights in 1689 gave women the right to vote.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"false. The Bill of Rights, 1689, confirmed the rights of Parliament and the limits of the king's power."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What is the name of the most famous cricket competition played between England and Australia?","choices":["The Ashes","The Six Nations Championship","The Grand National","The Australian Open"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The most famous cricket competition is the Ashes, which is a series of Test matches played between England and Australia."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was the biggest source of employment during the 18th century?","choices":["Fishing","Teaching","Aircraft industry","Manufacturing"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"During the 18th century, manufacturing jobs became the main source of employment in Britain."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"In 1314 the Scottish, led by Robert the Bruce, defeated the English at the battle of Bannockburn, and Scotland remained unconquered by the English.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Which of the following is an example of criminal offence?","choices":["Smoking in public places where it is not allowed","Disputes about faulty goods or services","Disputes about an unfair dismissal in the workplace","A dispute between the landlord and the tenants who have not paid the rent"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Smoking in public places. It is against the law to smoke tobacco products in nearly every enclosed public place in the UK. There are signs displayed to tell you where you cannot smoke."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which Scottish clan was killed for not taking the oath?","choices":["The MacLaine of Lochbuie","The McDowalls of Garthland","The Macpherson of Cluny","The MacDonalds of Glencoe"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The correct answer is the MacDonalds of Glencoe."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which two issues can the devolved administrations pass laws on?","choices":["Defence","Social security","Health","Education"],"correct":[2,3],"explanation":"Policy and laws governing defence, foreign affairs, immigration, taxation and social security all remain under central UK government control. However, many other public services, such as health and education, are controlled by the devolved administrations."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"The assassination of the Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria in 1914 led to which of the following wars?","choices":["The Crimean War","The First World War","The Civil War","The Second World War"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"On 28 June 1914, Archduke Franz Ferdinand of Austria was assassinated. This set off a chain of events leading to the First World War (1914-18)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the capital city of Scotland?","choices":["Glasgow","St Andrews","Edinburgh","Aberdeen"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The capital city of Scotland is Edinburgh."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"In 1833 the Emancipation Act abolished slavery throughout the British Empire.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the process by which many Scottish landlords destroyed individual small farms (known as 'crofts') to make space for large flocks of sheep and cattle?","choices":["The Black Death","The Corn Removal","The Highland Clearances","The Enlightenment"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"A process began which became known as the 'Highland Clearances'. Many Scottish landlords destroyed individual small farms (known as 'crofts') to make space for large flocks of sheep and cattle."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"The Falkland Islands are a British overseas territory and are part of the United Kingdom.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Falkland Islands are a British overseas territory. They are also linked to the UK but are not part of it."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which two of the following are Civil War Battles?","choices":["The Battle of Waterloo","The Battle of Marston Moor","The Battle of Naseby","The Battle of Agincourt"],"correct":[1,2],"explanation":"The Battles of Marston Moor and Naseby."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was the name of the activist group who fought for the women's right to vote?","choices":["Chartists","Beefeaters","Suffragettes","Quakers"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In the late 19th and early 20th centuries, an increasing number of women campaigned and demonstrated for greater rights and, in particular, the right to vote. They formed the women's suffrage movement and became known as the 'suffragettes'."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What UK landmark was voted as Britain's favourite view in 2007?","choices":["The Big Ben","Lake District","Snowdonia","The London Eye"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In 2007, television viewers voted Wastwater (Lake District) as Britain's favourite view."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who were the first people to live in Britain in what we call the Stone Age?","choices":["Farmers","Peasants","Hunter-gatherers","Pirates"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The first people to live in Britain were hunter-gatherers."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the movement against the authority of the Pope and the ideas of the Catholic Church that took place during the reign of Henry VIII?","choices":["The Reformation","The Enlightenment","The Glorious Revolution","The Renaissance"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The correct answer is the Reformation."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What do you need to do to apply for a National Insurance Number?","choices":["Contact the NHS","Contact the Department for Work and Pensions (DWP)","Contact your local MP","Ask you employer to get it for you"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"If you have permission to work in the UK, you will need to telephone the Department for Work and Pensions (DWP) to arrange to get a National Insurance number."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Which of the following is a major horse-racing event in England?","choices":["The Wimbledon Championship","Royal Ascot","The Open Championship","The Six Nations Championship"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Famous horse-racing events include: Royal Ascot, a five-day race meeting in Berkshire attended by members of the Royal Family; the Grand National at Aintree near Liverpool; and the Scottish Grand National at Ayr."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"How many members form a jury in Scotland?","choices":["12","14","15","20"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In Scotland a jury has 15 members."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What is known as Lent?","choices":["The 40 days before Christmas","The 40 days after Easter","The 40 days before Easter","The 40 days after Christmas"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The 40 days before Easter are known as Lent."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When was the last successful foreign invasion of England?","choices":["1415","1314","1066","1200"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Norman Conquest was the last successful foreign invasion of England in 1066."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"World War II started as a result of Germany invading which country?","choices":["France","Russia","Poland","Austria"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Second World War started when Hitler invaded Poland in 1939. Britain and France declared war in order to stop his aggression."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which flower is associated with Scotland?","choices":["The Shamrock","The Rose","The Daffodil","The Thistle"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The flower associated with Scotland is the thistle."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Police complaints can only be made by writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"false. Anyone can make a complaint about the police by going to a police station and writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved. Complaints can also be made to an independent body: the Independent Police Complaints Commission in England and Wales, the Police Complaints Commissioner for Scotland or the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which of the following is a responsibility of the Home Secretary?","choices":["Economy","Crime","Education","Defence"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Home Secretary is responsible for crime, policing and immigration."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When is St David's day celebrated?","choices":["1st March","17th March","23rd April","17th April"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"St David's day, patron of Wales, is celebrated on the 1st of March."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What happened to 'Mary, Queen of Scots' after she spent 20 years in prison?","choices":["She became Queen of England","She was sent to France","She escaped to Denmark","She was executed"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Mary was eventually executed, accused of plotting against Elizabeth I."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"What did Francis Crick discover?","choices":["The MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) scanner","The jet engine","The IVF (in-vitro fertilisation) therapy","The structure of the DNA molecule"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Francis Crick discovered the structure of the DNA molecule."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Northern Ireland and Scotland have their own banknotes, which are valid everywhere in the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How many national parks are there in England, Wales and Scotland?","choices":["25","15","18","42"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"There are 15 national parks in England, Wales and Scotland."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Is Northern Ireland part of Great Britain?","choices":["Yes","No"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Great Britain' refers only to England, Scotland and Wales, not to Northern Ireland."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"If you are a dog owner, which two things should your dog's collar have when you go out for a walk?","choices":["The owner's address","The owner's name","The dog's breed","The dog's name"],"correct":[0,1],"explanation":"All dogs in public places must wear a collar showing the name and address of the owner."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What day relates to the death of Jesus Christ?","choices":["Good Friday","Easter Sunday","Easter Monday","Ash Wednesday"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Easter takes place in March or April. It marks the death of Jesus Christ on Good Friday and his rising from the dead on Easter Sunday."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"A responsibility of the MPs is to represent everyone in their :","choices":["County","Estate","District","Constituency"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"A responsibility of the MPs is to represent everyone in their constituency."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was achieved with the Magna Carta?","choices":["It restricted the King's power","It increased the King's power","It restricted the rights of the farmers","It increased women's power"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The Magna Carta established the idea that even the king was subject to the law. It protected the rights of the nobility and restricted the king's power to collect taxes or to make and change laws. In future, the king would need to involve his noblemen in decisions."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Female genital mutilation (FGM) or taking a girl or woman abroad for FGM is illegal in the UK and it is a criminal offence.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What year were women given the right to vote?","choices":["1918","1925","1949","1914"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights and the right to stand for Parliament, partly in recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which two of the following are British overseas territories?","choices":["St Helena","Solomon Islands","Mauritius","The Falkland Islands"],"correct":[0,3],"explanation":"There are several British overseas territories, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands. They are linked to the UK but are not part of it."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who did the English defeat in 1588?","choices":["The Normans","The Romans","The Spanish Armada","The Saxons"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In 1588 the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who designed the Cenotaph?","choices":["Sir Norman Foster","Lancelot 'Capability' Brown","Sir Edwin Lutyens","Isambard Kingdom Brunel"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Sir Edwin Lutyens was responsible for designing many war memorials throughout the world, including the Cenotaph in Whitehall."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How often are the members of the Welsh government elected?","choices":["Every 5 years","Every 2 years","Every 4 years","Every 3 years"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"There are 60 members of the Welsh government or members of the Senedd (SMs) and elections are held every four years using a form of proportional representation."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"During which period did the Beatles become popular and social laws were liberalised?","choices":["1960s","1970s","1980s","1950s"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The decade of the 1960s was a period of significant social change. It was known as the 'swinging sixties'. There was growth in British fashion, cinema and popular music. Two well-known pop music groups at the time were The Beatles and The Rolling Stones. It was also a time when social laws were liberalised, for example in relation to divorce and to abortion in England, Wales and Scotland. The position of women in the workplace also improved."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"The Man Booker Prize is awarded in which of the following categories?","choices":["Films","Sport","Literature","Music"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Man Booker Prize for Fiction is awarded annually for the best fiction novel (literature) written by an author from the Commonwealth, Ireland or Zimbabwe. It has been awarded since 1968. Past winners include Ian McEwan, Hilary Mantel and Julian Barnes."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What sort of election takes place when a member of the Parliament (MP) dies or resigns?","choices":["Coalition","Pre-selection","Random selection","By-election"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"If an MP dies or resigns, there will be a fresh election, called a by-election, in his or her constituency."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the Turner Prize?","choices":["A literature award","A music award","A contemporary art award","A theatre award"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Turner Prize was established in 1984 and celebrates contemporary art. The Turner Prize is recognised as one of the most prestigious visual art awards in Europe."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which flower is associated with Northern Ireland?","choices":["The daffodil","The thistle","The shamrock","The rose"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The flower associated with Northern Ireland is the shamrock."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"The last battle between Britain and France was the battle of Waterloo.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"£100 is the highest value note in circulation in the UK.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"This statement is false."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Where is the Lake District National Park located?","choices":["Scotland","Wales","England","Northern Ireland"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Lake District is in England."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which two responsibilities will you have as a British citizen?","choices":["To buy food locally","To volunteer in a community project at least once a year","To look after yourself and your family","To respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions"],"correct":[2,3],"explanation":"If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should: respect and obey the law, look after yourself and your family, respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions, treat others with fairness and look after the area in which you live and the environment."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was born in Stratford-upon-Avon?","choices":["Jane Austen","Charles Dickens","William Shakespeare","Thomas Hardy"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"William Shakespeare was born in Stratford-upon-Avon, England."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Why is 1928 an important year in women's voting history?","choices":["Women were given the right to vote at the age of 18, the same as men.","Women were given the right to vote at the age of 25.","Women were given the right to vote at the age of 30.","Women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 1928, women were given the right to vote at the age of 21, the same as men."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What does Hogmanay refer to?","choices":["Christmas Day in Wales","New Year's Eve in Scotland","Christmas Day in Scotland","New Year's Eve in Wales"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In Scotland, the 31st of December (New Year's Eve) is called Hogmanay."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the capital city of Northern Ireland?","choices":["Cork","Edinburgh","Belfast","Dublin"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The capital city of Northern Ireland is Belfast."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following wars took place between 1899 and 1902 in South Africa?","choices":["The Hundred Years War","The Boer War","The First World War","The Crimean War"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Boer War took place between 1899 and 1902 in South Africa."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Northern Ireland uses a system called 'individual registration' and all those entitled to vote must complete their own registration form.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which two of the following policies are not controlled by the devolved administrations?","choices":["Health","Education","Defence","Immigration"],"correct":[2,3],"explanation":"Policy and laws governing defence, foreign affairs, immigration, taxation and social security all remain under central UK government control. However, many other public services, such as education, are controlled by the devolved administrations."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How old do citizens of the UK, the Irish Republic or the Commonwealth have to be to stand for public office?","choices":["18","21","16","25"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Most citizens of the UK, the Irish Republic or the Commonwealth aged 18 or over can stand for public office. There are some exceptions, including: members of the armed forces, civil servants and people found guilty of certain criminal offences."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"How did the Government promote policies of free trade during the Victorian Age?","choices":["Abolishing a number of taxes on imported goods","Abolishing the exportation of local produce","Preventing the importation of cheap raw materials","Preventing the importation of cheap grain"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"During Victorian times, the government began to promote policies of free trade, abolishing a number of taxes on imported goods. One example of this was the repealing of the Corn Laws in 1846. These had prevented the import of cheap grain. The reforms helped the development of the British industry, because raw materials could now be imported cheaply."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was Admiral Nelson?","choices":["One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans","A British officer in charge of the British army at the Battle of Waterloo","A British general who established the authority of the English Parliament","A British officer in charge of the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar against the Spanish fleet"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar against the Spanish fleet and was killed in the battle."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"During the Middle Ages, who were the serfs?","choices":["Peasants who had a small area of their lord's agricultural land","Soldiers who fought at the Battle of Trafalgar","Noblemen who formed part of the king's council of advisers","A group of skilled people from Holland who came to England during the Middle Ages"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Serfs were peasants who had a small area of their lord's land where they could grow food."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which invention lead to the rapid development of the industry in Britain during the 18th and 19th centuries?","choices":["The Radar","The Steam Power","The Jet Engine","The Turing Machine"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Industrial Revolution was the rapid development of industry in Britain in the 18th and 19th centuries. Britain was the first country to industrialise on a large scale. It happened because of the development of machinery and the use of steam power."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"MPs can only be contacted by post.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"You can contact MPs by letter or telephone at their constituency office, or at their office in the House of Commons. In addition, many MPs, Assembly members, MSPs and MEPs hold regular local 'surgeries', where constituents can go in person to talk about issues that are of concern to them."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What movement challenged the authority of the Pope?","choices":["The Swinging Sixties","The Reformation","The Suffragettes","The Enlightenment"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Reformation was a movement against the authority of the Pope and the ideas and practices of the Roman Catholic Church."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What English King introduced the Domesday Book?","choices":["King Henry V","King Henry IV","William the Conqueror","Harold, the Saxon king of England"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"William the Conqueror sent people all over England to draw up lists of all the towns and villages. The people who lived there, who owned the land and what animals they owned were also listed. This was called the Domesday Book."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What did 'the Butler Act' introduce in 1944?","choices":["Free primary education in England, Wales and Scotland","Free university fees in England, Wales, Scotland and Northern Ireland","Free primary and secondary education in England, Wales and Scotland","Free secondary education in England and Wales"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Richard Austen Butler became a Conservative MP in 1923 and held several positions before becoming responsible for education in 1941. In this role, he oversaw the introduction of the Education Act 1944 (often called 'The Butler Act'), which introduced free secondary education in England and Wales."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What is the small claims procedure?","choices":["An informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer","A procedure that helps people to make small home insurance claims in certain circumstances"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The small claims procedure is an informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What building was constructed in Hyde Park to hold the Great Exhibition of 1851?","choices":["The Crystal Palace","Buckingham Palace","Kensington Palace","Apsley House"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"In 1851, the Great Exhibition opened in Hyde Park in the Crystal Palace, a huge building made of steel and glass. Exhibits ranged from huge machines to handmade goods."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was Florence Nightingale?","choices":["An economist","A painter","A nurse","A poet"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Florence Nightingale was a nurse. She is often regarded as the founder of modern nursing."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who is the patron Saint of England?","choices":["St George","St Patrick","St David","St Andrew"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The patron Saint of England is St George."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where is Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park located?","choices":["England","Wales","Scotland","Northern Ireland"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park is located in the west of Scotland."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Wales has its own established church.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"There is no established Church in Wales or Northern Ireland."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What stories are associated with Geoffrey Chaucer?","choices":["The Cambridge Tales","The Eastbourne Tales","The Canterbury Tales","The London Tales"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series of poems in English about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"When is Boxing Day celebrated?","choices":["31st October","26th December","24th December","01st January"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Boxing Day is the day after Christmas Day (26th December) and is a public holiday."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the holiday when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day?","choices":["Credit Holidays","Branch Holidays","Bank Holidays","Business Holidays"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"There are public holidays each year called bank holidays, when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Why were women given the right to vote?","choices":["In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War","In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the Second World War","In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the Crimean War","In recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the Civil War"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights and the right to stand for Parliament, partly in recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What do you need to drive in the UK?","choices":["An 'L' plate","A National Insurance Number","A valid driving licence","An 'R' plate"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In the UK, you must have a driving licence to drive on public roads."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where does 'the Fringe' festival take place?","choices":["Fraserburgh","Edinburgh","Inverness","St Andrews"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Edinburgh Festival takes place in Edinburgh, Scotland, every summer. It is a series of different arts and cultural festivals, with the biggest and most well-known being the Edinburgh Festival Fringe ('the Fringe')."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How many members does the Welsh government have?","choices":["150","120","90","60"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"There are 60 members of the Welsh government or members of the Senedd (SMs) and elections are held every four years using a form of proportional representation."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"The names or photographs of young people found guilty of a crime can be published in newspapers or used by the media.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Members of the public are not allowed in Youth Courts, and the name or photographs of the accused young person cannot be published in newspapers or used by the media."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was Edward Elgar famous for?","choices":["He was a musician","He was a tennis player","He was a comedian","He was an actor"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Sir Edward Elgar (1857-1934) was a musician. His best known work is probably the Pomp and Circumstance Marches. March No1 (Land of Hope and Glory) is usually played at the Last Night of the Proms at the Royal Albert Hall."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following is not a British banknote?","choices":["£50","£25","£20","£5"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"There are no £25 notes in the UK."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where does the Scottish Grand National take place?","choices":["Fife","Edinburgh","Ayr","St Andrews"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Scottish Grand National takes place at Ayr."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"The laws passed after the Glorious Revolution marked the beginning of the ______.","choices":["Constitutional monarchy","Constitutional republic"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The laws passed after the Glorious Revolution marked the beginning of the constitutional monarchy."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"During the reign of Elizabeth I, a large fleet of ships was sent to England to conquer the country and to restore Catholicism, where did this fleet come from?","choices":["France","Portugal","Spain","Italy"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Elizabeth I became one of the most popular monarchs in English history, particularly after 1588, when the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What did the Habeas Corpus Act introduce?","choices":["That every prisoner has a right to a court hearing","A salary for members of Parliament (MPs)","Financial help for the unemployed, old-age pensions and free school meals","Measures to improve the conditions of workers"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The Habeas Corpus Act became law in 1679. This was a very important piece of legislation which remains relevant today. Habeas corpus is Latin for 'you must present the person in court'. The Act guaranteed that no one could be held prisoner unlawfully. Every prisoner has a right to a court hearing."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What did Emmeline Pankhurst fight for?","choices":["The right to liberty and security","The right for women to vote","Freedom of expression","The right to a fair trial"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Emmeline Pankhurst she set up the women's Franchise League in 1889, which fought to get the vote in local elections for married women. In 1903 she helped found the Women's Social and Political Union (WSPU). This was the first group whose members were called 'suffragettes'. The group used civil disobedience as part of their protest to gain the vote for women. In 1918, women over the age of 30 were given voting rights and the right to stand for Parliament, partly in recognition of the contribution women made to the war effort during the First World War."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is 'the Proms'?","choices":["An annual event that gives awards in a range of categories, such as best British group and best British solo artist","An annual cultural festival which includes music, dance, art and original performances largely in Welsh","An eight-week summer season of daily orchestral classical music concerts","Light-hearted plays with music and comedy"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Proms is an eight-week summer season of orchestral classical music that takes place in various venues, including the Royal Albert Hall in London."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"What was Isaac Newton known for?","choices":["The discovery of insulin","The discovery of gravity","The discovery of penicillin","The discovery of steam power"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Newton's most famous published work was Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica ('Mathematical Principle of Natural Philosophy'), which showed how gravity applied to the whole universe."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When did the WWI come to an end?","choices":["In 1922","In 1918","In 1945","In 1943"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In 1918\n"},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Is St Helena part of the UK?","choices":["Yes","No"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"British overseas territories, such as St Helena and the Falkland Islands are linked to the UK but are not part of it."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where is Theatreland?","choices":["Docklands","London's East End","London's West End","London's South End"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"London's West End, also known as 'Theatreland', is particularly well known for its theatres."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the UK currency?","choices":["Euro","Pound Sterling","Peso","Dollar"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The currency in the UK is the pound sterling (symbol £)."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What other name is given to Diwali?","choices":["The Festival of Lights","Ash Wednesday","Good Friday","Easter Monday"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Diwali is often called the Festival of Lights."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the Enlightenment?","choices":["A period of total peace in England","A period when new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed","A period when England became the largest empire the world had ever seen","A period of economic recovery after the Second World War"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Enlightenment was a period during the 18th century when new ideas about politics, philosophy and science were developed."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following charities helps the environment?","choices":["NSPCC","Shelter","Friends of the Earth","Crisis"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Friends of the Earth is an environmental charity."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following was a crucial aerial battle fought between Germany and Britain during WWII?","choices":["The Battle of Britain","The Battle of Worcester","The Battle of Dunbar","The Battle of Marston Moor"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The correct answer is the Battle of Britain."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was Margaret Thatcher famous for?","choices":["She fought for the right to vote for women","She was the first woman Prime Minister of the UK","She set up the women's Franchise League","She was the founder of modern nursing"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Margaret Thatcher was the first woman Prime Minister of the UK."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which two languages combined to become one English language?","choices":["Latin","Anglo-Saxon","Proto-Celtic","Norman French"],"correct":[1,3],"explanation":"After the Norman Conquest, the king and his noblemen had spoken Norman French and the peasants had continued to speak Anglo-Saxon. Gradually these two languages combined to become one English language."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"By law, radio and television coverage of the political parties must be balanced and so equal time has to be given to rival viewpoints.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where did the Spanish Armada come from?","choices":["France","Spain","Italy","South America"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In 1588 the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of the War Memorial located in Whitehall?","choices":["Dumfries","Cenotaph","Royal Crescent","The White Tower"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Cenotaph is a war memorial located in Whitehall."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"The UK government has never suspended the Northern Ireland Assembly.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Northern Ireland Assembly has been suspended on a few occasions."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"What kind of church did Scotland establish in 1560?","choices":["A Catholic church","A Protestant church"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In 1560, the predominantly Protestant Scottish Parliament abolished the authority of the Pope in Scotland and Roman Catholic religious services became illegal. A Protestant Church of Scotland with an elected leadership was established but, unlike in England, this was not a state Church."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When was the Domesday Book written?","choices":["After the Viking invasion","After the Norman conquest","After the last Roman invasion","After the Anglo-Saxon invasion"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"William the conqueror sent people all over England to draw up lists of all the towns and villages. The people who lived there, who owned the land and what animals they owned were also listed. This was called the Domesday Book, which gives a picture of society in England just after the Norman¬†Conquest."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"The Northern Ireland Assembly cannot make decisions on which two of the following issues?","choices":["Immigration","Education","Agriculture","Defence"],"correct":[0,3],"explanation":"The Northern Ireland Assembly can make decisions on issues such as: education, agriculture, the environment health and social services, but it cannot make decisions on immigration or defence issues."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"What should you do to make a complaint about the police (choose two answers)?","choices":["Write a complaint letter to the House of Commons","Go to the Police station directly","Write to the Chief Constable of the police force involved","Write to your MP"],"correct":[1,2],"explanation":"Anyone can make a complaint about the police by going to a police station and writing to the Chief Constable of the police force involved. Complaints can also be made to an independent body: the Independent Police Complaints Commission in England and Wales, the Police Complaints Commissioner for Scotland or the Police Ombudsman for Northern Ireland."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What flower did William Wordsworth write about?","choices":["Rose","Daffodil","Thistle","Shamrock"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"William Wordsworth wrote 'The Daffodils'."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When is St Andrew's day celebrated?","choices":["17th April","31st December","1st March","30th November"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"St Andrew's day, patron of Scotland, is celebrated on the 30th of November."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the architect that rebuilt Saint Paul's cathedral after the Great Fire in 1666?","choices":["Robert Adam","Sir Christopher Wren","Sir Norman Foster","Dame Zaha Hadid"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In 1666, a great fire destroyed much of the city, including many churches and St Paul's Cathedral. London was rebuilt with a new St Paul's, which was designed by a famous architect, Sir Christopher Wren."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When were the first coins in Britain made?","choices":["The Stone Age","The Bronze Age","The Iron Age","The Middle Ages"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The people of the Iron Age made the first coins to be minted in Britain."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was Emmeline Pankhurst?","choices":["A suffragette","A nurse","A doctor","A scientist"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Emmeline Pankhurst was born in Manchester in 1858. She set up the women's Franchise League in 1889, which fought to get the vote in local elections for married women. In 1903 she helped found the Women's Social and Political Union (WSPU). This was the first group whose members were called 'suffragettes'."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who did Britain fight against in the Crimean War?","choices":["Turkey","Russia","France","Germany"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"From 1853 to 1856, Britain fought with Turkey and France against Russia in the Crimean War."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"How old do you have to be to buy alcohol in the UK?","choices":["17","18","19","20"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"It is a criminal offence to sell alcohol to anyone who is under 18 or to buy alcohol for people who are under the\n"},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Which of the following is a Crown Dependency but not part of the UK?","choices":["Shetland","Isle of Wight","Isle of Man","Anglesey"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Channel Islands and the Isle of Man are closely linked with the UK but are not part of it. They have their own governments and are called 'Crown dependencies'."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Is the BBC controlled by the government?","choices":["Yes","No"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The BBC is the largest broadcaster in the world. It is the only wholly state-funded media organisation that is independent of government."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How many members does the Northern Ireland Assembly have?","choices":["12","60","90","108"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Northern Ireland Assembly has 90 elected members, known as MLAs (members of the Legislative Assembly)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was in charge of the British fleet at the Battle of Trafalgar?","choices":["Oliver Cromwell","The Duke of Wellington","Robert the Bruce","Admiral Nelson"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at Trafalgar and was killed in the battle."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was inscribed in the first coins to be minted in Britain during the Iron Age?","choices":["The names of Iron Age kings","The names of Iron Age Gods","The names of trees","The names of animals"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The people of the Iron Age made the first coins to be minted in Britain, some inscribed with the names of Iron Age kings."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Towns, cities and rural areas in the UK are governed by government appointed officials.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Towns, cities and rural areas in the UK are governed by democratically elected councils, often called 'local authorities'."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where is the Tate Art Gallery located?","choices":["Glasgow","Cardiff","London","Belfast"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Tate Britain and Tate Modern are in London."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"The version of the Bible created by King James I is known as:","choices":["Authorised version","Reformed version","Approved version","Unique version"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"One achievement of King James' reign was a new translation of the Bible into English. This translation is known as the 'King James Version' or the 'Authorised Version'."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What is the period of the 1960s known for?","choices":["A downgrade in manufacturing","A growth in British fashion and pop music","A shortage of water","A blockage of social laws"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The decade of the 1960s was a period of significant social change. It was known as the 'Swinging Sixties'. There was growth in British fashion, cinema and popular music."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Between 1680 and 1720 many refugees called Huguenots came to England, which country did they come from?","choices":["Pakistan","Germany","India","France"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Between 1680 and 1720 many refugees called Huguenots came from France."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What is the most famous tennis tournament played in the UK?","choices":["The Queen's Club Championships","Wimbledon","Roland Garros","The Aegon Championships"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The most famous tournament hosted in Britain is The Wimbledon Championships, which takes place each year at the All England Lawn Tennis and Croquet Club."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"MPs can only be contacted at their office in the House of Commons.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"You can contact MPs by letter or telephone at their constituency office, or at their office in the House of Commons. In addition, many MPs, SMs and MSPs hold regular local 'surgeries', where constituents can go in person to talk about issues that are of concern to them."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What is the day when jokes are published in newspapers and telecast on TV?","choices":["April Fool's Day","Boxing Day","Halloween","Valentine's Day"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"April Fool's Day, 1 April, is a day when people play jokes on each other until midday. The television and newspapers often have stories that are April Fool jokes."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which Scottish king defeated the English at the Battle of Bannockburn?","choices":["King Charles I","King James I","Admiral Nelson","Robert the Bruce"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 1314 the Scottish, led by Robert the Bruce, defeated the English at the Battle of Bannockburn, and Scotland remained unconquered by the English."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who invented the World Wide Web?","choices":["Sir Tim Berners-Lee","Sir Peter Mansfield","Sir Ian Wilmot","Sir Robert Edwards"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The inventor of the World Wide Web was Sir Tim Berners-Lee."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How are civil servants appointed and what political party do they belong to?","choices":["They are chosen on merit and form part of the Liberal Democrats party","They are chosen randomly and form part of the Conservative party","They are chosen randomly and are politically neutral","They are chosen on merit and are politically neutral"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Civil servants are chosen on merit and are politically neutral , they are not political appointees."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is known as the 'Dunkirk spirit'?","choices":["When the German air force bombed London and other British cities at night-time","The evacuation of Allied soldiers from France during World War II","When new social classes appeared after the Black Death","The period when many refugees called Huguenots came from France"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"During WWII as France fell, the British decided to evacuate British and French soldiers from France in a huge naval operation. Many civilian volunteers in small pleasure and fishing boats from Britain helped the Navy to rescue more than 300,000 men from the beaches around Dunkirk."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"You have to be at least 21 years old to serve on a jury.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Anyone who is on the electoral register and is aged 18 to 70 can serve on a jury."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should (choose TWO answers):","choices":["Respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions","Buy a house in the UK","Look after yourself and your family","Marry a British citizen"],"correct":[0,2],"explanation":"If you wish to be a permanent resident or citizen of the UK, you should: respect the rights of others, including their right to their own opinions, look after yourself and your family, respect and obey the law, treat others with fairness and look after the area in which you live and the environment."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following major sports event took place in the UK in 2012?","choices":["The Football World Cup","The Rugby World Cup","The Olympic games","The Eurocup Basketball"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The UK has hosted the Olympic games on three occasions: 1908, 1948 and 2012."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Charles I believed in the 'Divine Right of Kings' so he tried:","choices":["To rule without the Parliament","To rule with the approval of the Parliament","To raise money for the Parliament","To restore Catholicism in Britain"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Charles I believed in the 'Divine Right of Kings': the idea that the king was directly appointed by God to rule. He thought that the king should be able to act without having to seek approval from Parliament and he tried to rule without the Parliament."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"What is the Union Jack?","choices":["The Flag of the Commonwealth","The Flag of the United Kingdom","The shield used by British Knights","A trade union to protect workers rights"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Union Flag, the Flag of the United Kingdom is also known as the Union Jack."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was voted the greatest Briton of all time in 2002?","choices":["Mo Farah","Admiral Nelson","Winston Churchill","Clement Attlee"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In 2002 Winston Churchill was voted the greatest Briton of all time by the public."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following statements is true:","choices":["Women in Britain today make up about half of the workforce.","Women in Britain today make up about one quarter of the workforce."],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Women in Britain today make up about half of the workforce."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When is St George's day?","choices":["17th March","30th November","1st March","23rd April"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"St George's day, patron of England is celebrated on the 23rd of April."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which is the largest National Park in England?","choices":["Snowdonia","Loch Lomond and the Trossachs National Park","The Giant's Causeway","The Lake District"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Lake District is England's largest national park."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Boudicca, was a tribal leader who fought against which foreign invaders?","choices":["The Normands","The Vikings","The Anglo-Saxons","The Romans"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans was Boudicca, the queen of the Iceni."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following poems is about a group of people going on a pilgrimage?","choices":["The Canterbury Tales","All the world's a stage","A Midsummer Night's dream","Great Expectations"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Geoffrey Chaucer wrote a series of poems in English about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage. The people decided to tell each other stories on the journey, and the poems describe the travellers and some of the stories they told. This collection of poems is called The Canterbury Tales."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"How are public holidays called?","choices":["Bank Holidays","Workers Holidays","Business Holidays","Summer Holidays"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"There are public holidays each year called bank holidays, when banks and many other businesses are closed for the day."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"How did Charles II manage to escape to Europe after his defeat in the Civil War?","choices":["Hiding in a farmer's house","Riding a horse","Hiding in an oak tree","Swimming"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Charles II escaped from Worcester, famously hiding in an oak tree on one occasion, and eventually fled to Europe."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who defeated the Vikings?","choices":["Harold","Edward I of England","King Arthur","King Alfred the Great"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Anglo-Saxon kingdoms in England united under King Alfred the Great, who defeated the Vikings."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was William Caxton?","choices":["A poet who wrote about a group of people going to Canterbury on a pilgrimage","The first person in England to print books using a printing press","The first person to sail singlehanded around the world","The inventor of the television"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"William Caxton was the first person in England to print books using a printing press."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where do Beefeaters serve as tour guides?","choices":["The Houses of the Parliament","The Tower of London","The O2","The Big Ben"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Beefeaters serve as tour guides at the Tower of London."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"During the rebellion of the clans in Scotland, Bonnie Prince Charlie was supported by clansmen from which Scottish region?","choices":["Glasgow","Galloway","The Highlands","Edinburgh"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Charles Edward Stuart (Bonnie Prince Charlie) was supported by clansmen from the Scottish Highlands."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What religion did Elizabeth I follow?","choices":["She was a Protestant","She was a Catholic","She was a Buddhist","She was a Hindu"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Elizabeth the I was a protestant."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Who became famous for his tramp character in silent movies?","choices":["Sir Rex Harrison","David Niven","Richard Burton","Charlie Chaplin"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Charlie Chaplin became famous in silent movies for his tramp character."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which armed force was used in the Battle of Britain?","choices":["The Royal Navy","The Police Force","The Naval Service","The Royal Air Force"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The correct answer is the Royal Air Force."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"In the UK, you have to be 21 years old to be able to vote in a general election.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The present voting age of 18 was set in 1969 and (with a few exceptions) all UK-born and naturalised adult citizens have the right to vote."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following poets was inspired by nature?","choices":["John Masefield","Wilfred Owen","Siegfried Sassoon","William Wordsworth"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"British poets, including William Wordsworth, were inspired by nature."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Against which country did Britain fight at the Battle of Waterloo?","choices":["Germany","Italy","France","Spain"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In 1815, the French Wars ended with the defeat of the Emperor Napoleon by the Duke of Wellington at the Battle of Waterloo."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was William Wilberforce?","choices":["A poet","A sportsman","A politician","A musician"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"William Wilberforce, an evangelical Christian and a member of Parliament, also played an important part in changing the law. Along with other abolitionists (people who supported the abolition of slavery), he succeeded in turning public opinion against the slave trade."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Who is the spiritual leader of the Church of England?","choices":["The Archbishop of Canterbury","The Archbishop of London","The Archbishop of Birmingham","The Archbishop of Manchester"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The spiritual leader of the Church of England is the Archbishop of Canterbury."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"James I was King of which country before becoming King of England?","choices":["Wales","Ireland","France","Scotland"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"When Elizabeth I died, her cousin James VI of Scotland became King James I of England, Wales and Ireland and Scotland remained a separate country."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"Which of the following statements is correct?","choices":["Most shops in the UK open seven days a week.","All shops in the UK close on Sundays and bank holidays.","Most shops in the UK open only on weekends.","All shops in the UK open only on weekends."],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Most shops in the UK are open seven days a week, although trading hours on Sundays and public holidays are generally reduced."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which country sent a fleet of ships to England in 1588?","choices":["France","Germany","Spain","Italy"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Elizabeth became one of the most popular monarchs in English history, particularly after 1588, when the English defeated the Spanish Armada (a large fleet of ships), which had been sent by Spain to conquer England and restore Catholicism."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Where is the National Horseracing Museum located?","choices":["Edinburgh, Scotland","Newmarket, Suffolk","St Andrews, Scotland","Aintree near Liverpool"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"There is a National Horseracing Museum in Newmarket, Suffolk."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following castles is located in Scotland?","choices":["Crathes Castle","Caernarfon Castle","Bodiam Castle","Powis Castle"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Crathes Castle is located in Scotland."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was a famous Art Deco ceramic designer?","choices":["Alexander McQueen","Thomas Chippendale","Clarice Cliff","Mary Quant"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Britain has produced many great designers, from Thomas Chippendale (who designed furniture in the 18th century) to Clarice Cliff (who designed Art Deco ceramics) to Sir Terence Conran (a 20th-century interior designer)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When is St Patrick's day celebrated?","choices":["23rd April","30th November","1st April","17th March"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"St Patrick's day, patron of Northern Ireland is celebrated on the 17th of March."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"How are the members of the Northern Ireland Parliament elected?","choices":["By a system of proportional representation","Using a system of ranked voting","Using the first past the post system","Using a runoff system"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The Northern Ireland Assembly has 90 elected members, known as MLAs (members of the Legislative Assembly). They are elected with a form of proportional representation."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the first British Prime Minister?","choices":["Winston Churchill","Earl of Wilmington","Henry Pelham","Sir Robert Walpole"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The most important minister in Parliament became known as the Prime Minister. The first man to be called this was Sir Robert Walpole, who was Prime Minister from 1721 to 1742."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Which of the following actresses has not won an Oscar?","choices":["Tilda Swinton","Emily Watson","Dame Judi Dench","Kate Winslet"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"British actors to have won Oscars include Colin Firth, Sir Antony Hopkins, Dame Judi Dench, Kate Winslet and Tilda Swinton. Emily Watson has not won an Oscar yet."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"During the Enlightenment, Adam Smith developed ideas about:","choices":["Physics","Economics","Science","Engineering"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"During 'the Enlightenment' Adam Smith developed ideas about economics which are still referred to today."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who died at the Battle of Trafalgar?","choices":["Admiral Nelson","Henry VIII","Oliver Cromwell","Napoleon"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Admiral Nelson was in charge of the British fleet at Trafalgar and was killed in the battle."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When is Hogmanay celebrated?","choices":["25th of December","2nd of January","1st of January","31st of December"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In Scotland, the 31st of December is called Hogmanay."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Proceedings in Parliament are broadcast on television and published in official reports known as:","choices":["Canvassing","Hansard","Cabinets","Domesday Book"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Proceedings in Parliament are broadcast on television and published in official reports called Hansard."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following is a rugby competition?","choices":["The Scottish Grand National","The Wimbledon Championships","The Ashes","The Six Nations Championship"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The most famous rugby union competition is the Six Nations Championship between England, Ireland, Scotland, Wales, France and Italy."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Who appoints life peers in the House of Lords?","choices":["The Speaker","The Archbishop of Canterbury","The Prime Minister","The monarch"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Life peers are appointed by the monarch on the advice of the Prime Minister."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who mapped the coast of Australia?","choices":["James Cook","Admiral Nelson","Isaac Newton","Sake Dean Mahomet"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Captain James Cook mapped the coast of Australia and a few colonies were established there."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was the first war to be extensively covered by the media","choices":["The Boer War","The First World War","The Second World War","The Crimean War"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Crimean War was the first war to be extensively covered by the media through news stories and photographs."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following monuments is located in Wiltshire?","choices":["Hadrian's Wall","St Paul's Cathedral","Nelson's Column","Stonehenge"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Stonehenge stands in what is now the English county of Wiltshire."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the first Archbishop of Canterbury?","choices":["St Patrick","St Augustine","St Andrew","St Columba"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"St Augustine led missionaries from Rome, who spread Christianity in the south. St Augustine became the first Archbishop of Canterbury."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"How old do you have to be to go into betting shops or gambling clubs?","choices":["18","20","16","21"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"You have to be 18 to go into betting shops or gambling clubs."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"The system of government in the UK is a parliamentary democracy.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the traditional food of Northern Ireland?","choices":["Haggis","Pancakes","Paella","Ulster Fry"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Ulster fry is the correct answer."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was elected as British Prime Minister in 1945?","choices":["Clement Attlee","Winston Churchill","Harold Wilson","Harold Macmillan"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"In 1945 the British people elected a Labour government. The new Prime Minister was Clement Attlee."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"How many times has the UK hosted the Olympic games?","choices":["5","3","4","8"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The UK has hosted the Olympic games on three occasions: 1908, 1948 and 2012."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Why were canals built during the Industrial Revolution?","choices":["To link the factories to towns and cities and to the ports","To make space for the large fleet of British ships","To increase the number of water mills in the UK","To increase the amount of water in towns and cities"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Canals were built to link the factories to towns and cities and to the ports, particularly in the new industrial areas in the middle and north of England."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Are civil servants appointed by the government?","choices":["Yes","No"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Civil servants are accountable to ministers. They are chosen on merit and are politically neutral , they are not political appointees."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following countries helped Britain to develop the Concorde?","choices":["Germany","Norway","Italy","France"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Britain and France developed the world's only supersonic commercial airliner, Concorde."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which invention led to the development of Britain during the Industrial Revolution?","choices":["Magnetic Resonance Imaging","Steam power","Radar","Hovercraft"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The Industrial Revolution was the rapid development of industry in Britain in the 18th and 19th centuries. Britain was the first country to industrialise on a large scale. It happened because of the development of machinery and the use of steam power."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who was the tribal leader who fought against the Romans?","choices":["Columba","Claudius","Hadrian","Boudicca"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"One of the tribal leaders who fought against the Romans was Boudicca."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which two languages were used across England during the Middle Ages?","choices":["Welsh","Gaelic","Norman French","Anglo-Saxon"],"correct":[2,3],"explanation":"The Middle Ages saw the development of a national culture and identity. After the Norman Conquest, the king and his noblemen had spoken Norman French and the peasants had continued to speak Anglo-Saxon."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"In 1776, which British colonies declared their independence because they demanded that there should be 'no taxation without representation'?","choices":["North African","Asian","North American","South African"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"In 1776, 13 North American colonies declared their independence, stating that people had a right to establish their own governments."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When was England ruled by a republic and not by a monarch?","choices":["When Elizabeth I died without any successor","When Charles I was executed","When the Carta Magna restricted the king's power","When king Harold died after the Battle of Hastings"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"When Charles I was executed, England declared itself a republic, called the Commonwealth. It no longer had a monarch."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which film produced in the UK was one of the most commercially successful films of all time and one of the highest-grossing film franchises?","choices":["Harry Potter","Spider-man","The Lord of the Rings","Indiana Jones"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Some of the most commercially successful films of all time, including the two highest-grossing film franchises (Harry Potter and James Bond), have been produced in the UK."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When did the first farmers come to Britain?","choices":["10,000 years ago","6,000 years ago","15,000 years ago","2,000 years ago"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The first farmers arrived in Britain 6,000 years ago."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When did the First World War end?","choices":["At 12.00 pm on 11th November 1914","At 12.00 pm on 11th November 1918","At 11.00 am on 11th November 1914","At 11.00 am on 11th November 1918"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The First World War ended at 11.00 am on 11th November 1918 with victory for Britain and its allies."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"Can court orders be obtained to protect a person from being forced into a marriage?","choices":["Yes","No"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"true. Court orders can be obtained to protect a person from being forced into a marriage, or to protect a person in a forced marriage."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What medal did Mary Peters win in the 1972 Olympics?","choices":["She did not win any medals","Silver","Gold","Bronze"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Born in Manchester, Mary Peters moved to Northern Ireland as a child. She was a talented athlete who won an Olympic gold medal in the pentathlon in 1972."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"In England, Wales and Northern Ireland Youth Court cases are normally heard by (choose TWO answers)?","choices":["Up to 3 specially trained magistrates","A District Judge","A sheriff","Up to 5 specially trained magistrates"],"correct":[0,1],"explanation":"In England, Wales and Northern Ireland, if an accused person is aged 10 to 17, the case is normally heard in a Youth Court in front of up to three specially trained magistrates or a District Judge."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was invented by Alan Turing in the 1930s?","choices":["The jet engine","The television","The Turing machine","The ball pen"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"A Turing machine is a theoretical mathematical device invented by Alan Turing (1912-54), a British mathematician, in the 1930s."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which of the following tells us about how people lived in England just after the Norman Conquest?","choices":["The Domesday Book","The Book of Common Prayer","The Canterbury Tales","The Carta Magna"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"William sent people all over England to draw up lists of all the towns and villages. The people who lived there, who owned the land and what animals they owned were also listed. This was called the Domesday Book. It still exists today and gives a picture of society in England just after the Norman Conquest."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who led a team of scientists to 'split the atom' for the first time?","choices":["Alexander Fleming","Alan Turing","Ernest Rutherford","Sir Peter Mansfield"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Scientists led by Ernest Rutherford, working at Manchester and then Cambridge University, were the first to 'split the atom' and took part in the Manhattan Project in the United States, which developed the atomic bomb."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What song is sung by people in the UK and other countries when they are celebrating the New Year?","choices":["Auld Lang Syne","The British Anthem","Jingle Bells","White Christmas"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The song Auld Lang Syne, which is sung by people in the UK and other countries when they are celebrating the New Year (or Hogmanay as it is called in Scotland)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Who fought in the English Civil war of 1642?","choices":["The House of York and the House of Lancaster","The Anglo-Saxons and the Vikings","The Cavaliers and the Roundheads","The House of Fraser and the House of Stuart"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Civil war between the king and Parliament began in 1642. The country split into those who supported the king (the Cavaliers) and those who supported Parliament (the Roundheads)."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"Which two of these forts were part of Hadrian's wall?","choices":["Vindolanda","Maiden Castle","Housesteads","Grimsby"],"correct":[0,2],"explanation":"Parts of Hadrian's Wall, include the forts of Housesteads and Vindolanda."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What was the religion of the Puritans?","choices":["Hindu","Catholic","Sikh","Protestant"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Puritans were a group of Protestants who advocated strict and simple religious doctrine and worship."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"What is the name of Irish people who favoured complete independence from the UK in the 19th century?","choices":["Fenians","Quakers","Highlanders","Suffragettes"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The Irish Nationalist movement had grown strongly through the 19th century. Some, such as the Fenians, favoured complete independence."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Which two British pop music groups were famous during the Swinging Sixties?","choices":["The Rolling Stones","The Beatles","ABBA","Radiohead"],"correct":[0,1],"explanation":"The decade of the 1960s was a period of significant social change. It was known as the 'swinging sixties'. There was growth in British fashion, cinema and popular music. Two well-known pop music groups at the time were The Beatles and The Rolling Stones."},{"type":"The UK values and principles","question":"What is the minimum age required to drive a motorcycle?","choices":["16 years old","17 years old","18 years old","21 years old"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In the UK, you must be at least 17 years to drive a car or motorcycle and you must have a driving licence to drive on public roads."},{"type":"The UK government and your role","question":"The members of the House of Lords, known as peers, are elected by the people.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"false. The members of the House of Lords, known as peers, are not elected by the people."},{"type":"A long and illustrious history","question":"When did the Emancipation Act abolish slavery throughout the British Empire?","choices":["1835","1823","1807","1833"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 1833 the Emancipation Act abolished slavery throughout the British Empire."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Who is responsible for crime, policing and immigration?","choices":["The Chancellor of the Exchequer","The Foreign Secretary","The Speaker","The Home Secretary"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Home Secretary is responsible for crime, policing and immigration."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What kind of genre was the film Wallace and Gromit created by Nick Park?","choices":["A soap opera","A silent movie","An animated film","An action film"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Nick Park won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring Wallace and Gromit."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Anyone who is violent towards their partner , whether they are a man or a woman, married or living together , can be prosecuted.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"true. Anyone who is violent towards their partner , whether they are a man or a woman, married or living together , can be prosecuted."},{"type":"Global relations","question":"When was the United Nations set up?","choices":["After the First World War.","After the Second World War.","Before the First World War.","Before the Second World War."],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The UN was set up after the Second World War and aims to prevent war and promote international peace and security."},{"type":"Geography and landmarks","question":"Where is the Giant's Causeway located?","choices":["Scotland","England","Wales","Northern Ireland"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Giant's Causeway is a land formation of columns made from volcanic lava located on the north-east coast of Northern Ireland. It was formed about 50 million years ago. There are many legends about the Causeway and how it was formed."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"What happened to Mary, Queen of Scots, after being sent to prison for 20 years by her cousin Queen Elizabeth I?","choices":["She got married.","She was sent to France.","She was executed.","She was sent to Scotland."],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Mary was executed, accused of plotting against Elizabeth I."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"Which tribe came to Britain from northern Europe after the Romans left in AD 410?","choices":["The Gepids","The Jutes","The Frisians","The Burgundians"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Britain was invaded by tribes from northern Europe: the Jutes, the Angles and the Saxons."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What is one of the highest-grossing film franchises produced in the UK?","choices":["James Bond","Star Wars","The Lord of the Rings","Superman"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Some of the most commercially successful films of all time, including the two highest-grossing film franchises (Harry Potter and James Bond), have been produced in the UK."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Who can hear cases in Youth Courts in England, Wales and Northern Ireland (two answers)?","choices":["Specially trained magistrates.","Social workers.","District judges.","Members of the public."],"correct":[0,2],"explanation":"In England, Wales and Northern Ireland, if an accused person is aged 10 to 17, the case is normally heard in a Youth Court in front of up to three specially trained magistrates or a District Judge."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who came from the Netherlands to become the British monarch?","choices":["William II","Charles II","Edward II","George II"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In May 1660, Parliament invited Charles II to come back from exile in the Netherlands. He was crowned King Charles II of England, Wales, Scotland and Ireland."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Who can apply for the National Citizen Service programme?","choices":["14- and 15-year-olds","15- and 16-year-olds","16- and 17-year-olds","17- and 18-year-olds"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The National Citizen Service programme gives 16- and 17-year-olds the opportunity to enjoy outdoor activities, develop their skills and take part in a community project."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Nick Park has won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring:","choices":["Chariots of Fire","Wallace and Gromit","Four Weddings and a Funeral","Women in Love"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Nick Park, who has won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring Wallace and Gromit."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was the British scientist who co-discovered the structure of the DNA molecule in the 1950s?","choices":["Sir Ian Wilmot","Keith Campbell","James Watt","Francis Crick"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The structure of the DNA molecule was discovered in 1953 through work at British universities in London and Cambridge. This discovery contributed to many scientific advances, particularly in medicine and fighting crime. Francis Crick (1916-2004), was one of those awarded the Nobel Prize for this discovery."},{"type":"Demographics","question":"What percentage of the UK population has a parent or grandparent born outside of the UK?","choices":["Around 5%","Around 10%","Around 15%","Around 20%"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Nearly 10% of the population has a parent or grandparent born outside the UK."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"How old do you have to be to drive a moped in the UK?","choices":["15 years old","16 years old","17 years old","18 years old"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In the UK, you need to be at least 16 years old to ride a moped, and there are other age requirements and special tests for driving large vehicles."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was the leader of the Labour Party who introduced a Scottish Parliament and a Welsh Assembly?","choices":["James Callaghan","Clement Attlee","Gordon Brown","Tony Blair"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 1997 the Labour Party led by Tony Blair was elected. The Blair government introduced a Scottish Parliament and a Welsh Assembly."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"What is the maximum amount you can claim through the small claims procedure in Scotland and Northern Ireland?","choices":["£3,000","£5,000","£8,000","£10,000"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The small claims procedure is an informal way of helping people to settle minor disputes without spending a lot of time and money using a lawyer. This procedure is used for claims of less than £10,000 in England and Wales and £3,000 in Scotland and Northern Ireland."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"Which historical monument did William the Conqueror build?","choices":["St Paul's Cathedral","The Cenotaph","Dumfries House","The White Tower"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The White Tower in the Tower of London is an example of a Norman castle keep, built on the orders of William the Conqueror."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who became Prime Minister after Margaret Thatcher and played an important part in the Northern Ireland peace process?","choices":["James Callaghan","John Major","Tony Blair","Harold Wilson"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"John Major became Prime Minister after Margaret Thatcher and played an important part in the Northern Ireland peace process."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Who should you contact to report a terrorist activity?","choices":["Your local Council.","Your local MP.","Your local police force.","The Prime Minister."],"correct":[2],"explanation":"If you think someone is trying to persuade you to join an extremist or terrorist cause, you should notify your local police force."},{"type":"Sports and recreation","question":"Which Paralympic athlete has won gold medals for swimming at the 2008, 2012 and 2016 Paralympic Games?","choices":["Sophie Christiansen","Ellie Simmonds","Baroness Tanni Grey-Thompson","David Weir"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Ellie Simmonds is a Paralympian who won gold medals for swimming at the 2008, 2012 and 2016 Paralympic Games and holds a number of world records. She was the youngest member of the British team at the 2008 Games."},{"type":"Geography and landmarks","question":"Each of the UK countries is associated with a flower symbol, which country is associated with the rose?","choices":["Wales","Northern Ireland","Scotland","England"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The countries that make up the UK all have flowers which are particularly associated with them and which are sometimes worn on national saints' days. The flowers associated to each country are as follows: England , the rose, Scotland , the thistle, Wales , the daffodil and Northern Ireland , the shamrock."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Isambard Kingdom Brunel was responsible for:","choices":["The construction of the Great Western Railway.","The invention of the television.","The construction of the Tower of London.","The discovery of insulin."],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Brunel was originally from Portsmouth, England. He was an engineer who built tunnels, bridges, railway lines and ships. He was responsible for constructing the Great Western Railway, which was the first major railway built in Britain. It runs from Paddington Station in London to the south west of England, the West Midlands and Wales."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"What is the Commonwealth?","choices":["An organization responsible for the protection and promotion of human rights in its member countries.","A group of European and North American countries that have agreed to help each other if they come under attack.","An association of countries that support each other and work together towards shared goals in democracy and development.","An international organization that aims to prevent war and promote international peace and security."],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The Commonwealth is an association of countries that support each other and work together towards shared goals in democracy and development. Most member states were once part of the British Empire, although a few countries which were not have also joined."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"Under which name was the movement of opinion against the authority of the Pope during the times of Henry VIII known?","choices":["The Spanish Inquisition","The Holy Wars","The Reformation","The Enlightenment"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"The correct answer is the Reformation."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"What did Isaac Newton discover?","choices":["Gravity","Penicillin","Insulin","Lightbulb"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Newton's most famous published work was Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica ('Mathematical Principle of Natural Philosophy'), which showed how gravity applied to the whole universe. Newton also discovered that white light is made up of the colours of the rainbow."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"What kind of movies did Academy Award winner Nick Park specialise in?","choices":["Action movies","Animated movies","Thrillers","Horror movies"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"Britain continues to be particularly strong in special effects and animation. One example is the work of Nick Park, who has won four Oscars for his animated films, including three for films featuring Wallace and Gromit."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Which of the following is not a constitutional institution?","choices":["The Parliament","The cabinet","The armed forces","The police"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Constitutional institutions in the UK include: the monarchy, the Parliament (the House of Commons and the House of Lords), the Prime Minister, the cabinet, the judiciary (courts), the police, the civil service and the local government. The armed forces are not a constitutional institution."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"What food shortage caused the famine in Ireland?","choices":["Corn","Potato","Wheat","Oats"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"In the middle of the century the potato crop failed, and Ireland suffered a famine. A million people died from disease and starvation."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"The leader of the opposition appoints senior opposition MPs. They form a group whose role is to challenge the government and put forward alternative policies. What are they called?","choices":["Shadow Cabinet","Lobby groups","Civil servants","Support peers"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The leader of the opposition appoints senior opposition MPs to be 'shadow ministers'. Their role is to challenge the government and put forward alternative policies. They form the shadow cabinet."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"Which of the following are TWO responsibilities of the MPs?","choices":["Protect life and property","Represent everyone in their constituency","Help to create new laws","Scrutinise and comment on what the monarch is doing"],"correct":[1,2],"explanation":"MPs responsibilities include: to represent everyone in their constituency, to help to create new laws, to scrutinise and comment on what the government is doing and to debate important national issues."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"Who was the longest serving PM in the 20th century?","choices":["John Major","Sir Alec Douglas-Home","Robert Walpole","Margaret Thatcher"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Margaret Thatcher was the first woman Prime Minister of the UK. She was the longest-serving Prime Minister of the 20th century, remaining in office from 1979 until 1990."},{"type":"Geography and landmarks","question":"What name is given to the territories which are linked to the UK but not part of it?","choices":["Crown Dependencies","Offshore Territories","Crown Independencies","British Colonies"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"There are several islands which are closely linked with the UK but are not part of it: the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man. These have their own governments and are called 'Crown dependencies'."},{"type":"Historical figures","question":"What area did David Hume contribute to during the Enlightenment?","choices":["Architecture","Poetry","Cinema","Philosophy"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"David Hume was a famous philosopher who developed ideas about human nature during the 18th century and that have continued to influence philosophers over the years."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"What proportion of the population died as a result of the Black Death in England?","choices":["Half of the population","One third of the population","55% of the population","One quarter of the population"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"As a result of the Black Death, one third of the population of England died and a similar proportion in Scotland and Wales."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"What happened to Charles I after he was in prison?","choices":["He moved to Spain","He became a priest","He escaped to France","He was executed"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"Charles I's army was defeated at the Battles of Marston Moor and Naseby. Charles was held prisoner by the parliamentary army. As he was unwilling to reach any agreement with the Parliament, in 1649 he was executed."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"What are TWO responsibilities of the monarch?","choices":["To appoint the members of the cabinet","To advise, warn and encourage the Prime Minister's decisions on government policies","To debate important national issues","To appoint the government"],"correct":[1,3],"explanation":"The monarch does not rule the country but appoints the government, which the people have chosen in a democratic election. The monarch also has regular meetings with the Prime Minister and can advise, warn and encourage, but the decisions on government policies are made by the Prime Minister and cabinet."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"What kind of disaster was the Black Death?","choices":["A plague","An earthquake","A famine","A civil war"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The Black Death was a disease, probably a form of plague, that came to Britain in 1348."},{"type":"Global relations","question":"What country was in conflict with the UK for trading reasons during the 18th century?","choices":["Andorra","Germany","France","Luxembourg"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"During the 18th century, trading and settlements overseas sometimes brought Britain into conflict with other countries, particularly France, which was expanding and trading in a similar way in many of the same areas of the world."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"The Speaker is an MP, he or she represents a constituency and deals with the constituents.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"Geography and landmarks","question":"Where is Skara Brae, the best preserved prehistoric village in northern Europe, located?","choices":["Scotland","Wales","England","Northern Ireland"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Skara Brae on Orkney, off the north coast of Scotland, is the best preserved prehistoric village in northern Europe."},{"type":"Arts and culture","question":"Which of the following plays was written by William Shakespeare?","choices":["MacBeth","The Canterbury Tales","Doctor Faustus","The Mikado"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"William Shakespeare's most famous plays include MacBeth."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"Where was William the Conqueror from?","choices":["Italy","Portugal","France","Ireland"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"William the Conqueror was the Duke of Normandy (now northern France). He defeated Harold, the Saxon king of England, at the Battle of Hastings in 1066."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"How do you call the settlers from the Netherlands who went to war with the British in South Africa?","choices":["Blacksmiths","Boers","Conquistadors","Beefeaters"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"The British went to war in South Africa with settlers from the Netherlands called the Boers. The Boers fought fiercely and the war went on for over three years."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"In Northern Ireland, up to three specially trained magistrates or a District Judge are required for Youth Court cases.","choices":["TRUE","FALSE"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"This statement is true."},{"type":"Sports and recreation","question":"What made Roger Bannister famous?","choices":["He was the first man in the world to run a mile in under four minutes.","He won gold medals for ice dancing at the Olympic Games in 1984.","He won gold medals in rowing in five consecutive Olympic Games.","He was the first British to climb Mount Everest."],"correct":[0],"explanation":"Sir Roger Bannister was the first man in the world to run a mile in under four minutes, in 1954."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"Who was invited to invade and rule England in 1688?","choices":["The Duke of Medina Sidonia","Napoleon","King Philip II of Spain","William of Orange"],"correct":[3],"explanation":"In 1688, important Protestants in England asked William of Orange to invade England and proclaim himself king."},{"type":"Historical events","question":"Who was defeated at the Battle of the Boyne?","choices":["James I","James II","Richard I","Richard II"],"correct":[1],"explanation":"William of Orange defeated James II at the Battle of the Boyne in Ireland in 1690."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"What did the Factories Act of 1847 introduce?","choices":["It limited the number of hours that everybody could work to 10 hours per day.","It increased the number of hours that women and children could work to 12 hours per day.","It increased the number of hours that men could work to 12 hours per day.","It limited the number of hours that women and children could work to 10 hours per day."],"correct":[3],"explanation":"The Factories Act of 1847 limited the number of hours that women and children could work to 10 hours per day."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"What name is given to the group of MPs from the opposition?","choices":["Roundheads","Cavaliers","Shadow Cabinet","Quakers"],"correct":[2],"explanation":"Opposition MPs form the shadow cabinet and their role is to challenge the government and put forward alternative policies."},{"type":"Government and the law","question":"In which of the following matters can the Scottish Parliament legislate?","choices":["Education","Immigration","Security","Defence"],"correct":[0],"explanation":"The Scottish Parliament can legislate on: civil and criminal law, health, education, planning and additional tax-raising powers."}];
